<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bristolls military garden A sermon preached unto the worthy company of practisers in the military garden of the well governed citie of Bristoll. By Thomas Palmer, master of arts, and vicar of St. Thomas, and St. Mary Redcliffe in the same citie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838126</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838126</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2486</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08873)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2486)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1075:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bristolls military garden A sermon preached unto the worthy company of practisers in the military garden of the well governed citie of Bristoll. By Thomas Palmer, master of arts, and vicar of St. Thomas, and St. Mary Redcliffe in the same citie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device on title page.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>BRISTOLLS</hi> MILITARY GARDEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preached unto the</hi> Worthy Company of Practiſers <hi>in the Military Garden of the well</hi> Governed Citie of <hi>Bristoll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS PALMER, Maſter of Arts, and Vicar of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mary Redcl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> CITIE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Quam mol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tum eſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcire homines, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ant galeati.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. 7. 1635.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Perlegi hanc Concionem habitam Bristolia à <hi>M<hi rend="sup">ro</hi> PALMER</hi> Sanctae Mariae de Redcliffe Vicario, unà cum daplici Epistolâ Dedicatoriâ, quae continent folia <hi>14<hi rend="sup">em</hi>,</hi> in quibus non reperio al quid ſanae doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae aut bonis moribus repugnans, quo minus cum pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licâ utilitate imprimi queant, ita tamen ut ſi non intrà tres menſes typis mandentur, haec licentia ſit omninò irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>GVILIELMUS HAYWOOD</hi> R. R. P. Archiep. Cant. Capell. domest.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND TRULY NOBLE, PHILIP Earle of Pembrooke and Montgomery, Lord <hi>Chamberlaine of His Majesties Noble Family,</hi> &amp;c. Lord high Steward of the City <hi>of</hi> BRISTOLL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Reverend Doctor of our Church did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly dedicate his expoſitions of this firſt Booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> unto that <hi>Julium Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Willet.</note> that Mirrour of Martiall Activitie, Prince <hi>Henry.</hi> To whom then can I bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſecrate my explication of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, this ſmall parcell of the ſame Booke than unto your Honour? unto whom the ſame Prince gave the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Prize for your unparallell'd dexterity in the feates of Armes. As my diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:2486:3"/>is Martiall: ſo my Dedication doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover one qualitie of a Souldier, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. In daring to kiſſe ſo Honorable a hand with ſo poore a Preſent. But my Particular ſervice, and the generall obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of our City (whereof your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath the gratious Protection) have given the incouragement. Though this poore Souldier is preſt for your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſervice, yet (without your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paſſe) like one of the forlorne hope it ſhall dye in deſpaire, and bee buried in ſilence. If (like the Centurion) you ſhall bid him goe, Hee dares enter the Liſt of a doubtfull Cenſure. His Dialect is (like the language of a Souldier) plaine and blunt. His weapon is the Sword of the Spirit. His poſture is (like a Churchman) upon his knees: upon which your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Orator doth daily pray. That the daies of your Honour may bee as the daies of Heaven, and the Glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Period of your daies. So praieth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humbly devoted Servant, and unworthy Chaplaine, <hi>THOMAS PALMER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Richard Holworthy</hi> Maior, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>William Cann,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>William Hobſon,</hi> Sheriffes of the Citty of <hi>Bristoll:</hi> To Captaine <hi>Taylor,</hi> Captaine <hi>Aldworth,</hi> Captaine <hi>Elbridge;</hi> Captaines of the Traine Bands. To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Long.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">At the time of my Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> then Preſident: Mr. <hi>Walter Ellis,</hi> now Preſident of the Military Garden: And to all the reſt <hi>of that Martiall Societie.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould the exerciſe of Armes be generally laid aſide, that Respond in our Engliſh Liturgie, might bee taken in the ſtricteſt acception of a literall Senſe. <hi>There is none that fighteth for us, but onely Thou O God.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed that all the Lords People were Prophets: So Gods Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:2486:4"/>wiſh that everyone of the Lords People were a <hi>Moſes,</hi> An able Souldier, a compleat Warriour to fight the Battels of the Lord of Hoſts. His Maieſty hath granted, and by his Counſell confirmed a Freedome unto your City, for your practiſe of Martiall Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline: It was your owne Petition. Then let not your Omiſſion of Exerciſe returne a <hi>Quod petit ſpernit</hi> unto ſo gratious a Commiſsion. <hi>Saul</hi> armed <hi>David,</hi> as you ſhall finde in this diſcourſe. And <hi>David</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately put himſelfe into action Our King hath in like manner armed you, that you may gird on your Swordes, and exerciſe your Armes with ſafety. You that are Starres to fight in your courſe againſt <hi>Siſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> prove not falling Starres: Fall not from the diligent proſecution of ſuch an Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intendment. A houſe begunne, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finiſhed, is called the Founders folly. Proceede then upon this Honourable founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Leaſt that become your folly, which is your Glory. Let your <hi>Councell houſe</hi> give incouragement to your <hi>Campus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> your field of Martiall exerciſe. Let
<pb facs="tcp:2486:4"/>it not bee ſaid of any in your Cittie, Hee is a good Merchant, but a bad Souldier. As they pay unto their King the Cuſtome of their Goods; let them pay unto their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the Cuſtome of their Bodies, in the Cuſtomary Practice of Armes. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that they that will not, dare not beare Armes. And when neede requires, will prove rather a burthen, then a help unto their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.<note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 5.23.</note> Liable unto the curſe of <hi>Meros,</hi> and the Inhabitants thereof, becauſe they come not out to help the Lord againſt the mighty. Improve your ſervice on the Land, to be anſwerable to your experimented dexterity on the Sea; and J ſhall not eaſily finde your Parallell. I am ſure thas in your Spirituall Service,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſpecially <hi>Redcliffe,</hi> which for a Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chappell is not paralleld by any Church in our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumvmnium pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochialium (quas unquam vidi) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legantiſſima. Cambden.</hi>
               </note> for the ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of your Churches,<note n="*" place="margin">For our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, we are generally obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged unto the religious care of our Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Diocaeſan.</note> and the generall cofor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity both of Clergy and Laity, you give place unto none. Both your Policy and Religion have imboldned mee to dedicate this ſling of <hi>David,</hi> to your Nurſery of Armes. And my ſelfe to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your fellow Souldier in the Lord: THOMAS PALMER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2486:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BRISTOLLS</hi> MILITARY GARDEN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 SAMUEL 17. chap. and part of the 39. verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And David ſaid unto Saul, I cannot goe with theſe: for I have not proved them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt of Challenges (that ever we read of) is diſcovered in this Chapter,<note place="margin">The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> and had his paſſe from the mouth of an uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Philiſtine, a <hi>Goliah:</hi> accepted &amp; anſwered by a true Iſraelite, a <hi>David.</hi> This Duell was performed not in a private, but a pitched field: not in the time of peace, but in the action of warre. It was rather a generall Battell, then a ſingle Combate. Both of them fight for the body of an army, and a whole army fights in their bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> though as yet but obſcure, yet no private man. He was the annointed of the Lord, the appointed of God for this deſigne.<note n="*" place="margin">Licet quoſdam ſingulare certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men iniviſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina prodat hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria, nunquam tamen ut pro lege teneatur, divina ſanxit auctoritas. <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celot. Jur. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. lib. 4.</hi>
               </note> No warrantable patterne for our moderne Duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, who being but private perſons unſheath
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2486:6"/>the particular ſword of revenge in triviall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels: who for the breath of a lye will venture the breath of their noſtrils. Like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> to fight upon a private quarrell, and in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſlay a man,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.25.</note> is but <hi>armata nequitia,</hi> armed impietie.<note n="*" place="margin">Duellum est iſſicitum, niſi per revelatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> divinam ſit ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum. Sicut David in nomine Domini ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re certamen ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit contra Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſicut divinae juſtitie executor. <hi>Lyra in locum.</hi>
               </note> But <hi>David</hi> was armed with a more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full quarrell, when he was <hi>in qpparatu militari,</hi> in his preparation for armes. <hi>Saul</hi> armes <hi>David, v.</hi> 38. And <hi>David</hi> makes choice of his armes in this verſe: for the whole verſe runs thus. <hi>And David girded his ſword upon his armor, &amp; he aſſaied to goe: for he had not proved them. And David ſaid unto Saul, I cannot goe with theſe: for I have not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body of my Text divides it ſelfe into three parts.<note place="margin">The Analy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall diviſion.</note> 1. The Souldier, <hi>David.</hi> 2. His refuſall: <hi>I cannot goe with theſe.</hi> 3. The reaſon of his refuſall: <hi>for I have not proved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe three particular Circumſtances will afford us three ſubſtantiall Aphoriſmes of warre.<note place="margin">The Syntheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Firſt, the Souldier was <hi>David,</hi> and that a Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer, not a preſt Souldier. Conſider him here as a Martialliſt, not as a Duelliſt. For hee was a member of the Army, as well as a Champion for the Army. Then from this Inſtrument I note the lawfulneſſe of the Action. The lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of warre. It is not mine, but S. <hi>Austines</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>Noli existimare neminem placere Deo poſſe qui rebus bellicis ministrat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad Bonifac.</note> 
               <hi>In his enimerat San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus David, cui Dominus tam magnum perhibuit te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium.</hi> Suppoſe not the action of warre un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for any, wherein <hi>David</hi> was an Agent,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2486:6"/>whereof God himſelfe gave ſuch a notable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie. Secondly, <hi>Davids</hi> refuſall was not of the Action, but of the armes. <hi>I cannot goe with theſe.</hi> There is a choiſe of others intimated in the refuſall of theſe weapons. Though he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe, hee uſed his owne. Hence I note that there is both a neceſſitie, and a choiſe of armes. Laſtly, the reaſon of his refuſall was his want of skill at thoſe weapons: <hi>for I have not proved them.</hi> Hence I note the neceſſitie of a Military diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, of a Military exerciſe. Of theſe three Martiall propoſitions in their order, as I ſhall be enabled by the God of order.</p>
            <p>From <hi>David</hi> the warlike Precedent here in my text, my firſt propoſition was this. That the Action of warre is lawfull.</p>
            <p>For the explication, and application whereof I will methodically diſcover the Originall of warre.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Then the Nature of warre.</item>
               <item>Then the lawfulneſſe of warre.</item>
               <item>And then in what caſes it may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, the Originall.<note place="margin">Originall of warre.</note> If you demand when warre beganne. I muſt anſwere by an inverted ſpeech of our Saviours. <hi>Non ſic erat in principio.</hi> It was not from the beginning. God created the world, as <hi>Salomon</hi> built his Temple, hee uſed no Iron tooles that made a noiſe. The voice that made the world was a ſtill voice. The foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was laid in peace. When man was created the worlds <hi>Augustus,</hi> there was a generall peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2486:7"/>all the Creatures, in their ſubmiſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, in their union among themſelves. But when hee that was to governe the Creatures could not governe himſelfe, this bleſſed union was converted into a bloody warre. The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fell from man when man fell from God. The fall of man was the raiſing of a double war. Man againſt himſelfe, there was <hi>bellum innatum,</hi> or <hi>connaturale,</hi> an inteſtine war, the ſpirit againſt the fleſh. And the ſoones of men againſt the ſonnes of men; there was <hi>bellum nationale,</hi> a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall warre. The one internall, the other exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. This was the firſt Originall of warre.</p>
            <p>For the Nature of it.<note place="margin">The nature of warre.</note> Some define warre to be a violent and hoſtile diſſention undertaken by a lawfull edict for the repreſſing of injuries. This is a true inferiour active definition. But God who is a man of warre knowes beſt how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it. He hath proclaimed it unto the world by a Propheticall trumpet, To be a divine ſcourge for ſinne in the hand of the warriour, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 10.26. It is a ſcourge. A divine ſcourge. A ſcourge for ſinne.</p>
            <p>It is a ſcourge.<note place="margin">Warre is a ſcourge.</note> Warre is the ſword of God to puniſh ſinne: the ſcourge of God to whip out ſecuritie. The father of diſcontent, the Mother of change. A fury that is attended by ſword, fire, famine and murder. A miſerable neceſſity in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. A neceſſary Corrector of the worlds im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie. Are not theſe laſhes ſufficient to prove it a feareful ſcourge? It is <hi>virga furoris,</hi> the ſcourge of Gods fury. The ſword of the warriour is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2486:7"/>Gods rod of Iron. The that will not tremble at it ſhall periſh under it.</p>
            <p>Yet ſome deſperate wretches (having nought to looſe) entertaine no newes with better wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then the rumour of warre.<note place="margin">The abuſe of this ſcourge.</note> Warre is Gods Scourge, the Campe his houſe of Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yet<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtat. lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Animal.</note> like hungry vultures, they are never well till they follow it. Decayed Souldiers, (ſuch as wholly depend upon warres, pretend a Warrant for this their bloody deſire.<note n="*" place="margin">Penes caeteros imperii praemia, penes ipſos ſervitii neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> In the time of peace they can commonly ſhew no coin but markes. It is an abuſe that ſavours neither of Chriſtianity nor policy, that any approoved Souldier ſhould be put to his ſhifts.<note place="margin">Tacitus. Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>Iulium Sidus Iulius Caeſar</hi> had never ſuch a malevolent aſpect, as at any time to ſuffer it. But though miſery may conſtraine a man to deſperate reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, it doth not warrant them.</p>
            <p>The ſumme is this. The uſe of many things may be good (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) yet the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves naught. The uſe of a Souldier is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but to be a profeſt Souldier, to live no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but by blood and ſpoile, is no way warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nehemias</hi> builder may be the Souldiers Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme: A ſword in one hand, a trowell in the other, with <hi>Caeſars</hi> motto inverted: <hi>Ex utroque miles.</hi> A Souldier muſt have both one hand to fight, another to worke. If there bee no uſe of the ſword, he muſt make uſe of the trowell: He muſt get his living as by blood, ſo by ſweat, as he is beſt accommodated, by the ſweat either of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2486:8"/>body, or braine. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> were both Souldiers, and Shepheards; when they left the Army,<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt. <hi>205.</hi> ad Bonifac.</note> they followed the Flocke. <hi>Pacem habere debet voluntas, bellum neceſsitas.</hi> Warre ſhould not be our delight, but our neceſſity. For a man to ſerve in the cauſe of his Countrey is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.<note n="*" place="margin">Qui ſolum queſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpectant; velubi, cauſa dubia eſt, ultrò ac citra neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſeſe ad mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam offerunt. Eſtius. lib. <hi>3.</hi> in ſentent. diſt. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> But to bee a Mercenary ſlave unto any quarrell, or Religion, is more heatheniſh, then Chriſtian. The Lord will ſcatter thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in warre: and what profeſſion more ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then the Mercenary ſouldier? I thinke that <hi>David</hi> was as valiant as the beſt of theſe. And yet he did not leape into his Armes, untill God was blaſphemed, his King like to be unthroned, and his Countrey endangered.</p>
            <p>Now as Warre is a Scourge,<note place="margin">Warre a Divine Scourge.</note> ſo it is a Divine Scourge. God himſelfe hath beene knowne to be the motive, miſſive, and permiſſive Author.</p>
            <p>The motive Author.] The Lord ſtirred up the Philiſtines, and the Arabians againſt <hi>Iudah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. And the ſame Lord ſtirred up the Spirits of the Medes, and Perſians againſt <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Eſa,</hi> 13.17. When the forces of the enemies came againſt them, they ſhot the Arrowes; but the Lord may be ſaid to bend the Bow.</p>
            <p>The miſſive Author.] The Lord ſent againſt the kingdome of <hi>Iudah,</hi> bands of the Aramites and bandes of the Caldees. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 24. And the ſame Lord ſent <hi>Nebuchadneſſar</hi> againſt <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to deſtroy it. <hi>Ier.</hi> 25.9. when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies bent their forces toward them, they came not ſo much of themſelves, as about the Lords buſineſſe.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2486:8"/>
            <p>The Permiſſive Author. Though the Lord give motion, and miſſion to the enemy; yet they cannot prevaile without Gods Permiſſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his aſſiſtance. The Lord delivered the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites into the hands of the ſpoiler that ſpoiled them: As it is in the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Iudges.</hi> And the ſame Lord delivered <hi>Goliah</hi> into the hands of <hi>David,</hi> as it is in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>In the action of Warre Kings are but Gods Liefetenants or at moſt his Colonels.<note place="margin">God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of warre, therefore ſhould bee our confidence in warre.</note> God is the Generall, the chiefe Leader. Let him be the higheſt pitch of our confidence. We ſhall never neede to feare the foe, if wee have Him to our friend; nor to dread any enemy, if ſo mighty a Generall be on our ſide. As the action of War is the Lords, The Lord is a Man of Warre, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. So the end of Warre,<note place="margin">In victory, God is to have the praiſe.</note> Victory is the Lords, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. God hath the key of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and when it ſhall pleaſe Him to lend us that key, it ſhould open our lippes to ſet forth his praiſe.</p>
            <p>And as God is the <hi>Terminus à quo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods Glory ſhould bee the principall end of warre. <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
               </note> ſo let him be the <hi>Terminus ad quem.</hi> As warre is from the Lord, ſo let it be for the Lord. If <hi>Caeſars</hi> honour was touched, his Souldiers were ſo prodigall of their blood, ſo deſperately furious, that they were invincible. They gave unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which was <hi>Caeſars:</hi> let us give unto God, that which is Gods; the expenſe of our deareſt blood for the maintenance of his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>As Warre is a Scourge, a divine Scourge,<note place="margin">Warre is a ſcourge for ſin.</note> it is a Scourge for ſinne. It is almoſt a generall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2486:9"/>ſurmiſe in the World, that warre is but a thing of courſe, becauſe it hath beene common in all ages.</p>
            <p>But wee muſt know that a juſt God never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts a puniſhment without a juſt cauſe. Wee take notice of a ſecondary cauſe of warre, the pride or malice of the enemy: Not the primary impulſive cauſe the ſinne of a People, the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of a Nation. Warre is a puniſhment for ſin. The Lord of Hoſts affirmes it. If he ſinne, ſaith the Lord;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.</note> there is the primary impulſive cauſe, and that is ſinne. I will chaſten him with the rod of men; there is the ſecondary inſtrumentall cauſe, the Sword, and fury of the enemy. Warre is ſent into the World for our ſinnes, to correct us for them, to deterre us from them. Warre is a divine ſcourge for ſinne.</p>
            <p>Thus you have heard the originall of Warre, and the Nature of Warre. The lawfulneſſe of it I thus prove:</p>
            <q>
               <l>By the courſe of Nature.</l>
               <l>By the courſe of Religion.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Firſt by the courſe of Nature.<note n="*" place="margin">Quideulpatur in bello? an quod moriuntur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque moritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri: ut dominen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in pace vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturi? Hoc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendiſſe ti midorumeſt, non religioſorum. Auguſt. cont. Manich.</note> The deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of kingdomes, the devaſtation of Cities, the prophanation of Holy things, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſlaughters that are wrought in the fury, and heate of Warre, have made the cowardly conſciences of the Manichee and the Anabaptiſt, to ſuppoſe warre to be unnaturall. It is true that warre may ſeeme unnaturall, being the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of nature in her individualls: And yet is truly naturall, as it is the preſerver of nature in her ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2486:9"/>It is the bread of tear's as it is deſtructive, but it is the bread of neceſſity as it is defenſive.<note n="*" place="margin">Nocendi cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas libido do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minandi, &amp;c. Haec ſunt quae in bellis iure cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantur. <hi>Auguſt. idid.</hi>
               </note> Take away the hunger of Ambition, and the thirſt of Blood, and Warre ſhould not bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtefull unto the moſt tender conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Natura non deeſt in neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, &amp;c. <hi>Thom. 1. p. q. 76. a. 5.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> is of opinion, that as nature hath given to bruite beaſts hornes, hooſes, teeth and talents for offence, and defence: So having left man deſtitute of theſe, ſhee hath given him rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and hands in ſtead of theſe. Reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent offenſive, and defenſive weapons: hands to compoſe and uſe them. Now the onely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and lawfull action wherein to imploy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, is the action of Warre.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Violentiae per vim repulſio eſt ſecundum jus naturale.</hi> Gratia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. decret. diſtinct. 1. Warre lawfull by the courſe of Religion.</note> 
               <hi>Vim vi repellere licet.</hi> It is a rule of nature to repell force by force.</p>
            <p>As warre is lawfull by the courſe of Nature, ſo alſo by the courſe of Religion. Religion, and obedience unto God binde all Men to guard themſelves either with the offenſive or defenſive meanes of ſafety, with a ſubmiſſion of the iſſue unto the Will of the principall Agent, the Lord of Hoſts. The Spirit of Truth is not the ſpirit of errour, to perſwade us to an error in religion. But the ſame ſpirit was upon <hi>Iehazael</hi> exhorting <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that they ſhould not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, becauſe the battell was not theirs, but Gods, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Offences muſt come ſaith our Saviour, and woe unto them by whom they ſhall come, but not unto them by whom they ſhall bee decided. Both Nature and Religion doe conclude that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2486:10"/>warre muſt take place where equity is excluded. It brings the fatall and finall compremiſer of Nationall controverſies. The rule of war is no way oppoſite unto the rule of faith: <hi>Abraham</hi> made warre, yet loſt not his faith in the action; for it yet lives more renowned then his victory.<note n="*" place="margin">Abſurda pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp; in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos Principes admodum inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſa eſt ea cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdam aſſertio, bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non aliud eſſe, quàm com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune multorum homicidium, ac latrocinium. <hi>Eſtius in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. lib. 3. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 33.</hi>
               </note> Is it religiouſly lawfull for the ſubordinate Magiſtrate to inflict a ſevere puniſhment upon a particular violence? and ſhall it not bee lawfull for the Supreme, (who cannot appeale higher then himſelfe) to cut off ſuch by the hand of warre who offer a publike violence to himſelfe and to his kingdome? God as hee is univerſall, ſo he is juſt; and a generall act of juſtice is no way derogatory unto the glory of God.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemes that our Saviour is no friend to warre, when he tells us that all they that take up the ſword ſhall periſh by the ſword. I anſwere, that place is meant of ſuch as take up the ſword of revenge, before a lawfull authority hath put it into their hands. <hi>David</hi> in this Chapter tooke up the ſword, yet periſhed not, but proved vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious: But <hi>Saul</hi> armed <hi>David</hi> before he uſed his armes; there was <hi>Davids</hi> authority.</p>
            <p>If that other place bee objected<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5.39.</note> that hee which ſhall ſmite thee on thy right cheek, turne to him thy left.<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. in Serm. de puero Centur.</note> Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> makes the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that this and the like precepts are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, <hi>magis ad praeparationem cordis, quàm ad opus quod in aperto fit, &amp;c.</hi> for the inward preparing of the minde unto a charitable diſpoſition in our private injuries: not to cut off the generall action
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2486:10"/>of warre, which muſt have a greater reference to the publike, then to the private good. When the ſouldiers came to <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> hee bad them to be contented with their wages, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their wages. Hee doth direct their calling, not reject it: A calling therefore no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory unto the glory of God.</p>
            <p>And thus you have heard the Originall of warre, the nature of warre, and the lawfulneſſe of warre. I will now demonſtrate in what caſes it may bee lawfull: moſt of which I finde liſted in the Warlike proceedings of <hi>David</hi> here in my Text.</p>
            <p>The end is the firſt in intention,<note place="margin">In what caſes warre may bee lawfull.</note> though the laſt in execution: And I finde the firſt legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Davids</hi> proceedings to be <hi>in fine,</hi> in the end for the which they were undertaken. They were, <hi>pro Lege, pro Rege, pro Grege;</hi> for his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for his King, and for his Country. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. Secondly, <hi>In modo,</hi> in the manner of it. It was defenſive, <hi>verſ.</hi> 36. which though it doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an offenſive warre, it precedes it in equity. Thirdly, <hi>In auctoritate,</hi> in the lawfull authority. He had both the approbation and commiſſion of his Prince. <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. Theſe are the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with thoſe three things which <hi>Aquinas</hi> makes requiſite unto a lawfull warre.<note place="margin">Aquin. 2a. 2a. quaeſt. <hi>40.</hi> artic. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Authoritas Principis, Canſa justa, Intentio recta.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt, lawfull Authority.</note> A lawfull Commiſſion, a juſt Occaſion, an upright Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>22.</hi> cont. Fauſt. cap. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, warre muſt have a lawfull Commiſſion, that is, the authority of the Prince.<note n="*" place="margin">Laconica Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchia. Ariſt. Polit. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Suſcipiendi
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2486:11"/>belli authoritas, atque Conſilium penes Principem ſit, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Non pertinet ad privatam perſonam bellum movere ſine Principis autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, quia poteſt jus ſuum in jadicio ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioris proſequi. <hi>Nichol. de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellis. lib. 4. diſtinct. 25.</hi>
               </note> The authority of levying Forces, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming Warre, belongs to the Prince. It is the Prerogative of ſoveraignty to have the ſole power of Warre and Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Opera magis pertinent ad imperantem quàm ad exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem.</note>If this juriſdiction were granted to inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, what could enſue but the confuſion of a State! They that offended in this point amongſt the Romans, were in caſe of Treaſon. Our owne kings have been ſo ſeverely jealous in this caſe; that ſome of their Subjects have beene ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous whether (without Commiſſion) they might levy forces for the repreſſing of Rebels: Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it a more Politique ſafety to be too ſlow, then to forward: None being legally accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted publike enemies, untill by ſupreme authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they are ſo proclaimed. They that fall to ſpoyling upon a private motion, are capitall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both to Prince, and State.<note n="*" place="margin">Reum faciat Regem iniquitas imperandi. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentem autem Militem eſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat ordo ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi. <hi>Auguſt. cont. Manich. Secondly, the goodneſſe of the cauſe.</hi>
               </note> But where there is the authority of the Prince, the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ought not to queſtion the goodneſſe of the cauſe.</p>
            <p>The cauſe doth denominate Warre, as well as Martyrdome: and the goodneſſe of the cauſe doth crowne them both. <hi>Partem quam inſpicit juſtam ibi dat Palmam,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi> God doth uſually crowne that part with victory, which is armed with equity.<note n="*" place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>Frangis, &amp; attollit vires in milite cauſa;</hi> The cauſe as it is good or evill, dulleth or whetteth the courage of the Souldier. Polity as well as religion hath made the diſcovery.<note n="*" place="margin">Philip. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> This is the reaſon why Princes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2486:11"/>when they would picke a quarrell with their neighbours, though it be unjuſt, yet they alwaies pretend the cauſe to bee faire and honeſt.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice of the cauſe conſiſts in theſe points. Firſt that it be neceſſary.<note n="*" place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>4.</hi> li. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Instum bellum quibus neceſſarium, &amp;c.</hi> That war is juſt to whom it is neceſſary, who have no other refuge but in armes. It muſt not be upon every ſleight occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that the treaſure of a kingdome ſhould be conſum'd, and the flower of her ſubjects cut off. Neceſſitie, not ambition muſt bee the cauſe of warre: A State that is brought to a ſolide matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is better preſerved by a ſafe peace, than enlarged by a doubtfull warre. <hi>Adrian</hi> the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour-held it the ſafeſt ſtrength to pacifie his neighbours with peaceable conditions. That warre is juſt which is either defenſively or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſively neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pugnabe pro ſacris, &amp; legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, pro aris &amp; focis. <hi>Melanct. praeſat. com. in epiſt. ad Rom.</hi> In publices hoſtes omnis bomo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. <hi>Tert. Apol. c. 2.</hi>
               </note>Defenſive warre is that which is made in defence of our Religion, of our countrey,<note place="margin">Defenſive war.</note> of our lives, and of our liberty. This was the caſe of <hi>Ioab. Be ſtrong, and let us be valiant for the people, and for the Cities of our God.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.12. This was the juſtice of the Romans upon the Gaules, with other Barbarous intrenching neighbours. The ſame juſtice had the antient Brittanes againſt the Romanes, Saxons, Danes, and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, though not with the ſame ſucceſſe. In this caſe the cauſe is unqueſtionably juſt: But in no caſe againſt a lawfull Soveraigne.<note n="*" place="margin">Quid ſi Rex impia jubeat? Neparete. At malè multator: patere. Saravia de imperand. au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. Eccles. <hi>10.4</hi>
               </note> If kings command ſuch things as are abſolutely evill, we muſt not reſiſt in body, but in ſpirit, not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2486:12"/>what they injoyne, but tollerating what they inflict.<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.4.</note> In this caſe it is better to be a Martyr than a Traitour.</p>
            <q>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione querentes?</q>
            <p>The Injuries that may arme a Prince unto an offenſive warre are theſe.<note place="margin">Offenſive war.</note> Either when the law of Nations is infringed. As when a harmeleſſe paſſage is denied unto a deſolate nation.<note n="*" place="margin">Innoxius tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus filiis Iſrael negabatur, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ideo justa bella gerebant. <hi>Aug. in quaeſt. numeri.</hi> Juſta bella ſolent definiri, ſi gens vel civitas non reddit quod per injuriam ablatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Juſtum eſt bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ex edicto geritur de rebus repetendis. <hi>Iſid. Etymolog. l. 20</hi>
               </note> This juſtified the warre of the Iſraelite with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morite. Or when a Prince intrencheth upon that which is anothers, or with-holds it. <hi>Bellum quod rebus repetitiis geritur.</hi> Saith <hi>Tully.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Qui facit ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum bellum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um facit quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid capit ab hoſte quouſque ſibi ſit ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum de omni damno, veldonec ipſe hoſtis offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ſe adjus, &amp; velit ſatisfacere <hi>Nichol. de Or. bellis. l. 4. diſt. 25</hi>
               </note> A warre that is made after demand of things wrongfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or unjuſtly detained. This is the uſuall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell betwixt bordering kingdomes. * But if ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction be offerd, it is not juſtice to proſecute them by armes who ſubmit themſelves to the law of armes. The French refuſing thoſe faire offers made by the blacke Prince, gave him the happy occaſion of their unfortunate overthrow in the field of Poicters.</p>
            <p>This Caſe is as currant upon the ſea, as upon the Land, upon the ſtay or ſeaſure of our ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and goods in forraigne parts, if reſtitution be denied. The Prince may recover it by way of Reprizall. Much more may hee ſuppreſſe the violence of ſea-theeving Pyrats.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Qui medio venantur in aequore puppes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who bid men to ſtand upon the Ocean.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thoſe ſea vermine or rather the Devills water-Rats. Thoſe ſea Guls that are the perpetuall plague unto noble traffique. Thoſe Monſters of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2486:12"/>the ſea who raiſe a ſtorme in faire weather: and<note n="*" place="margin">Fallit Pontus &amp; ipſe fidem.</note> make men to ſuffer ſhipwracke in the haven. The Prophet denounceth a woe unto thoſe that ſpoile where they are not ſpoiled. Such roguing roving Pirats, if the law cannot ſuppreſſe them, the Cannon ſhould ſubvert them.</p>
            <p>And moſt of all it is lawfull for a Prince to defend the Title and Juriſdiction of his Seas: and offend thoſe who would intrench upon them. If Neceſſitie make a cauſe lawfull, this is moſt lawfull, becauſe moſt neceſſary. This caſe may be ours. The Sea is our Wall. And our beſt (though wooden) Battlements is our Navy. It was an experimentall concluſion of judicious <hi>Rawleigh,</hi> that the chiefe ſtrength of our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes conſiſts in our ſea forces. The ſafegard of our kingdome, the terrour of our enemy is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſteered at the helme. Our moving tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are our beſt forts, our winged-horſes our beſt Cavaleery, and victory is ſooner ſpied from our maine top than from our maine battell.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cuſtodit te Princeps ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus, debes ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ei tributum. <hi>Theophylac. in Luc. cap. 20.</hi> Inexpugnabile munimentum eſt amor civium: <hi>Senoc.</hi>
               </note>And God be thanked, it is a provident care of our gratious Soveraigne to incircle our Iland with a ſtately Royall Navy. Let us praiſe God for him, and be thankfull unto him in our loyall and liberall aſſiſtance.<note n="*" place="margin">Quis dabit ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, ſi publicum ceſſabit ſubſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um? Deo decimas, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi cenſum da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> Let not our purſe bee narrow, becauſe our ſeas are ſo.<note n="*" place="margin">Imperator ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegium eſſe ſcribit, de eo quod à principe factum eſt diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. <hi>Saravia de imperand. au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. lib. 2. c. 55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Demosthenes</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Treaſure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſinewes of war. And the Convulſion of theſe finewes may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the body of a ſtate, if not overthrow it.</p>
            <p>To queſtion the deſignes of a Soveraigne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a want both of judgement and loyaltie.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2486:13"/>The Romanes Souldiers when they were ſent out by their Senate, knew not at their departure the place where they ſhould fight. And this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique ignorance made neither the common people the more curious: nor the common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier the leſſe fortunate.</p>
            <p>The deſignes of State ſhould direct our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, not buſie our tongues: wee ſhould pray for their conſultations, not prye into their counſels. What <hi>Ioab</hi> ſaid concerning God himſelfe; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me (with reve rence) to invert it concerning Gods Deputy.<note n="*" place="margin">Inſuperabiles niſi ſeparabiles. <hi>2 Sam. 10.12.</hi>
               </note> Let us be ſtrong, and let us be valiant for our People, and for the Cities of our God, and let our Lord the King doe what is good in his eyes.</p>
            <p>Beſides,<note n="*" place="margin">Sanctaolim apud Ethnicos jura belli firma, &amp; inviolata pacis fuerunt ſoedera. Cic. de Offic. lib. <hi>1,</hi> &amp; deſenectute.</note> If leagues or covenants be not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; or if the fame of a Prince bee abuſed by diſgrace; or violence offered unto his Perſonall Inſtrument, his Embaſſadour, an offenſive warre may bee a lawfull courſe of revenge. Upon the like injury done unto <hi>Davids</hi> meſſengers by the king of Ammon, <hi>David</hi> revenged it by armes, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. Or if a reall injury bee done unto a Princes friend, Allyes or Confederates, it is a warrantable ground for an offenſive warre. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury was done unto <hi>Lot</hi> by his violent ſurpriſall: And <hi>Abraham</hi> his kinſ-man reſcued him by the ſword.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Offic.</note> 
               <hi>Fortitudo quaeper bella defendit à latronibus ſocios,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Populus Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſociis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendis terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium potitus eſt. <hi>Cicer.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>plena juſtitia eſt.</hi> To defend our oppreſſed friends from the violence of the oppreſſour, is the height of Juſtice. This kinde of defence laid the firſt foundation of the Roman Monarchy.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2486:13"/>
            <p>And thus I have diſcovered in what caſes warre may bee lawfull; and yet none of theſe lawfull, but in caſe of extremity. But as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity muſt force us to the action of warre:<note n="*" place="margin">Sicut bellanti, &amp; reſiſtenti vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia redditur: ita victor capte miſericordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> jam debetur; maximè in que pacis perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio non timetur: <hi>Auguſt. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac.</hi>
               </note> So in the execution there muſt bee no extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity either of rigour, or cruelty, It is neither Honour to kill our enemies diſ-armed, nor Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to kill our priſoners in cold blood, unleſſe our owne ſafety doe inforce it: which was the caſe of our Engliſh, when they put their Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to the ſword after the battell of <hi>Poicters.</hi> But the Women, the Children, and the Aged, who cannot bee the ſubject of our ſeare,<note n="*" place="margin">Thou ſhalt not ſlay the in nocent. Exod. 23.7.</note> ſhould not bee the ſubject of our cruelty, but ſhould be exempted from the fury of the Souldier; ſave where God and the ſuperiour Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the contrary.</p>
            <p>And thus warre being lawfull in the Action,<note place="margin">An upright in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in war.</note> lawfull in the Execution, there muſt alſo bee <hi>intentio recta,</hi> an upright intention. And that will be diſcovered in the lawfull end. <hi>Finis eſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in intentione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The End is the firſt Object of the intention. The ultimate end of warre, muſt, bee Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as I have already proved.<note n="*" place="margin">Non Pax quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur ut bellum exerceatur; ſed bellum geritur ut pax acquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Auguſt. ad Bonifac.</hi>
               </note> The ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate end, muſt bee Peace and Tranquillity.<note n="*" place="margin">Definitur bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſſe ſtudium Pacis. Aquin. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>40.</hi> a. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t mali coerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, &amp; honi ſubleventur.</note> What ſhould bee the end of a bloody warre, but a bleſſed Peace? <hi>Sapientes Pacis cauſe bellum gerunt.</hi> Wiſe men maintaine Warre, to obtaine Peace: — <hi>Pax optima rerum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2486:14"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quas homini noviſſe datum eſt. Pax una Triumphis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Innumeris potior.</hi> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace the beſt Miſtreſſe that a man can court:</l>
                  <l>To which a world of triumphs do come ſhort.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Peace is the worlds Jubile, the Crowne of a body Politique: the Supporter both of Church and Common-wealth. In Peace, the Goſpell findes a free and a glorious paſſage. In Peace, Faith the mother of Charity is aboundantly fruitfull in good workes. In Peace every one ſits quietly under their owne Vine, and enjoyes the fruite of his owne labour. But in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Warre our Plow-ſhares ſhould be turned into Swords, and our Sithes into Speares: our Garments ſhould rowle in blood. There would be a famine of Bread, a cleaneneſſe of Teeth, a dearth of all good things. Our Faith ſtaggerd, the lippes of the Prieſt that ſhould preſerve knowledge, ſealed up: the tongue of the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemour ſet at liberty: Holy things prophaned: the Church deſpiſed. Then that Petition in our Engliſh Lyturgy is as needefull, as warrantable: <hi>From battell and murther, and from ſudden death, good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, our feare might bee the leſſe, were every Souldier a <hi>David,</hi> as religious, as valiant. Therefore as <hi>Davids</hi> Action hath beene a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full precedent of warre, ſo let <hi>David,</hi> Perſon be a religious Parterne for a Souldier: which ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2486:14"/>bee the particulat Application of the generall Propoſition.</p>
            <p>He was a juſt Man, adorned with all vertue;<note place="margin">David a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</note> valiant beyond compariſon, yet moderate and courteous. Thus he is characteriz'd by<note n="*" place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ioſephus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee that beares Armes with <hi>David,</hi> ſhould beare his Character. Though every Souldier canot be a worthy with <hi>David,</hi> yet like him, he ſhould be a worthy Souldier, a Man after Gods owne heart, as religious as reſolute. As Saints may beare Armes; ſo they that beare Armes, ſhould be Saints. As God is a Man of Warre; ſo a Man of Warre, ſhould be a Man of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quàm mitis <hi>David,</hi> humilis ſpiritu, ſedulus corde, facilis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatu, fort is in praelio, manſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in imperio? <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note>In Gods liſt in the time of the Law, they were ſanctified Ones, which God himſelfe ſet apart for Military imployment, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 13.3.<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> had a Train-Band in his Houſhold: and he trained them up as well for Gods Service as his owne. This was the reſolution of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> I and my Houſe will ſerve the Lord. An honourable Service: God was the Lord of his Houſe, though his Houſe was a Campe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of Campes under the Goſpell, that on the bels of their horſes, ſhould be written Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Zach. 16.20.</note>In the liſt of the Goſpell you ſhall finde a faithfull Centurion. A devout <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who feared not the enemy, yet feared God: And Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories have regiſtred the beſt Souldiers ſometimes for the beſt men. <hi>Iulians</hi> thundring Legion. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> who was as good as great. And the <hi>Theodoſii</hi> who were as pious as victorious.</p>
            <p>The good life of the Generall ſhould bee a Sermon unto the Souldiers. And the good lives
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2486:15"/>of the Souldiers ſhould bee a repetition of that Sermon.<note n="*" place="margin">Juſtum bellum eſſe debet, ergo religione non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reret. <hi>Caſ. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. lib. 3. cap. 10.</hi>
               </note> I am perſwaded that the religious, exact, and impartiall Diſcipline of the <hi>Sueden</hi> Army, made them ſo conſtantly victorious. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion makes men valiant. <hi>The Righteous are bold as a Lion, Prov.</hi> 28.1. How can they feare the Enemy, that feare not Death, their gate unto Heaven? Religion is prevalent. We muſt bee <hi>Iacobs,</hi> or wee cannot bee <hi>Iſraels</hi> prevailing with God, and then we ſhall prevaile over men. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion confines a Souldier unto the obedience of his Commander. Like the <hi>Iſractite</hi> to <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> or the ſervant to the <hi>Centurion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon why the Souldiers of our time do ſo degenerate, is becauſe our Captaines, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the courſe of<note n="*" place="margin">Dinit Galba legi, à ſo Milite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non emi. Tacit.</note> 
               <hi>Galba.</hi> They doe buy, not chuſe their Souldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Legio à delectu Militum dicta.</hi> A band of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers is denominated from their choiſe. If they be not ſelevted, they looſe that title. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of an Army, ſhould not<note n="*" place="margin">Ex omnium gentium Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie.</note> (like <hi>Hannibals</hi>) conſiſt of the ſcumme of the Sea, of the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Land. A Commander ſhould have more then a common care in the choyce of the common ſouldier. A matter of great weight, but of little regard. Warre is now counted but the ſpleene of a body politique, to draine out the ill humours.<note n="*" place="margin">Pecuniola pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur: &amp; ecce coeunt aliqui igneti, igneran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſque, purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta urbium, quibus ab ege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem, &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma flagitia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi neceſſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do eſt, aſſueti la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociniis, bello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tes.</note> When occaſion of ſervice is offered, tatter'd Jayle-birds, and maſterleſſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grants are the greateſt part of maſter Conſtables choice. Amongſt whom it would grieve the ſould of any honeſt ſubject to be an Aſſociate.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2486:15"/>
            <p>It is no Chriſtian policy to chuſe ſuch ſinfull inſtruments for ſuch a ſerious Action. God will not bee the Leader of that Army, where ſinne raignes in the maine battell. Sinne is the onely <hi>Ramora</hi> that ſtoppes the happy proceedings of the moſt numerous Army. A guilty Conſcience doth chill the blood, and dull the edge of the moſt daring reſolution. The ſight of woundes and death muſt needs ſtartle that wreteh, who hath had the wounds and death of his Saviour too often in his mouth, but never in his heart. And the terrour of death muſt needes affright him, who cannot expect the death of the body, without the damnation of the ſoule. A ſouldier muſt be prepared for death, as well as for danger, which none can be, but he that is Religious. Let us fight with our ſinnes, before wee fight with our enemies. The conqueſt of the former will aſſure us of the latter conqueſt. Then ſhall wee be bleſſed in our going out, and in our comming in, then our enemies ſhall be ſmitten before our face, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.36.<note n="*" place="margin">Donabit cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanti victoriam qui certandi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit audaciam. <hi>Goliam</hi> magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robuſtum, armis terribilem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentique turba munitum <hi>David</hi> ſolus, parvus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inermis uno lapidis ictu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtravit. Auguſt. contra quinque her. in principto.</note> If they be <hi>Davids</hi> (though their enemies were <hi>Goliahs</hi>) they ſhall bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours: not onely in their life, but in their death. Though they dye in Warre, they ſhall depart in Peace. Everlaſting Peace ſhall be the Crowne of their temporall conflicts, if they bee religious <hi>Davids,</hi> and fight the Lords quarrell.</p>
            <p>And thus I paſſe from <hi>David</hi> the lawfull Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent of warre, and the religious Parterne of a ſouldier: I come now to his refuſall, which was not of the Action, but of the Armes.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2486:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot goe with theſe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is as I told you,<note place="margin">There is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of arms.</note> a choice of others inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the refuſall of theſe weapons: whence I noted, that there is both a neceſſity, and a choice of Armes. A neceſſity, for <hi>David</hi> went not without weapons. A choice, for hee refuſed ſome, and made choice of others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was arm'd, though but weakely: He had an offenſive weapon a ſling, ſaith the Text. A defenſive weapon, a breaſt-plate ſaith <hi>Ioſephus.</hi> There is a neceſſity of Armes: we have now no ſufficient warrant that God will deſtroy our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies immediately, as he did the Hoſt of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib;</hi> or miraculouſly, as he did <hi>Iericho.</hi> God doth now confine us unto the meanes: To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe this, were to contemne the ſubordinate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, which God hath appointed. As it is an Atheiſticall impiety to preferre the ſword of <hi>Gideon,</hi> before the ſword of the Lord: So it is an unwarrantable preſumption to ſeparate the ſword of the Lord, and the ſword of <hi>Gideon.</hi> The ſword of the Lord is to direct: the ſword of <hi>Gideon</hi> to execute. The ſword of the Lord is the primary efficient: the ſword of <hi>Gideon</hi> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate inſtrument. The firſt without the laſt will doe nothing: the laſt without the firſt can doe nothing. <hi>David</hi> did not truſt in his bow, nor his ſword, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.6. yet hee might uſe them both. He might uſe the inſtrument, and truſt in the principall Agent.</p>
            <p>The danger of theſe times doth prompt us to the practice of our Saviours leſſon. Let him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2486:16"/>that hath no ſword ſell his coat and buy him one, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.38.<note n="*" place="margin">Reipublicae fundamentum bonae leges &amp; bona Arma. <hi>Mach. Princip. cap. 12.</hi>
               </note> If there be not a ſpeare, and a ſhield in this our Iſrael, to ſay God ſhield us will be no warrant of ſafety. If our enemies have the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of cruelty in their habitation, let us have the weapons of ſafety in ours.</p>
            <q>— Ebrietas in Pralia trudit inermem.</q>
            <p>It is a deſperate ſottiſhneſſe that brings unar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſouldiers into the field. <hi>Non de pugna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Veget.</note> 
               <hi>ſed de fuga cogitant, qui nudi in acie exponuntur ad vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera.</hi> Vnweapond ſouldiers thinke more of the flight, then of the fight; for they can onely take blowes, not give them. It is not now<note n="*" place="margin">Pugno benè uteris inquit, C. <hi>Craſſus,</hi> feſtivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taxans iner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem, cui pro gladio pugno ſit utendum. <hi>Eraſ. 6. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na à pugnis.</hi> Souldiers goe not now into the field (as in the worlds infancy) to cuffe or ſcratch one another. Every ſtroke of Warre (if not repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the force of Armes) doth wound or kill. It is the loſſe of a limme, or of a life. Therefore we muſt have armes for our men, as well as men for our Armies.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Chron. 12.33.37.</note> 
               <hi>Zebulon, Reuben, Gad, Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the voluntary aſſiſtants of <hi>Dauid,</hi> came not unarmed, but completely furniſhed with all their uſuall inſtruments of Warre. Armes are as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as hurtfull; as defenſive, as offenſive.<note n="*" place="margin">Armaab ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo.</note> A weapon ſcars a theefe, and the want of it makes a theefe.<note n="*" place="margin">Wee muſt have a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as well as a Spirituall Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oply.</note> Armes are the ſtrength of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the terrour of the Enemy. The want of Armes, doth arme the adverſary, and make him with a ſecure boldneſſe to rob and ſpoile.</p>
            <p>This neceſſity of Armes gives a deſerved checke unto the trecherons tranſporters of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. This is an inſenſible miſchiefe, too much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2486:17"/>winked at, too much tolerated. The danger here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be ſooner felt, then diſcovered: and the publike State will ſmart for it, if private offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders doe not.</p>
            <p>Now as there is a neceſſity,<note place="margin">There is a choice of armes.</note> ſo there is a choice of Armes:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Armae antiqun, manus, unguts, denteſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fnerunt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Handes,<note place="margin">Lucret.</note> nayles, and teeth, were the old Primitive Armes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe were ſeconded with ſtones,<note place="margin">Herodetus.</note> and clubs for offenſive weapons; and the skinnes of Beaſts for defenſive harneſſe. But as the times, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes grew more cruell, ſo the weapons more dangerous.<note place="margin">Euſebius prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. Evang.</note> That <hi>Moſes</hi> was one of the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors of Warlike weapons, is ſomewhat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable: becauſe the Jewiſh Magazine was (in thoſe times) the beſt furniſhed with weapons both Defenſive; as Helmets, Breaſt-Plates, coats of Male, Habergions, Greaves, Bucklers, Shields, and Targets: Offenſive; Swordes, Daggers, Speares, Lances, Hand-ſtaves, Battle-Axes, Darts and Slings. The ſame weapon, which <hi>David</hi> made choice of in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>But we are now no more confin'd unto their weapons, then unto their policy: Succeſſion of times, and the cruelty of invention, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the Catalogue of Armes; and have made them more exquiſite, more terrible. The Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of ancient times (ſaith <hi>Bodine</hi>) being compared with ours, are rather childiſh toyes, then Warlike weapons. Wee ſhould now bee rather mad then politique, to make choyce of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2486:17"/>Stone-bowes, and Slings againſt Cannon and Musket: our choice of Armes, muſt bee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated unto the times. Wee muſt be ſure to match, if not over-match our enemies in the convenience and force of Armes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Infeſtiſque obvia ſignis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Signa pares aquilas, &amp; pila minantiae pilis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wee muſt not bee to chuſe our weapons,</l>
               <l>when we are to encounter the enemy.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Paulus Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius dicebat Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liti haec tria eſſe curanda: corpus validiſſimum, Arma apta, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum adſubitae imperia paratum Liv. lib. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note>And as Armes muſt be fitted to the times, ſo to the Perſons that beare them.<note n="*" place="margin">Sueton.</note> 
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> would have his ſouldiers accompliſhed with the compleateſt Armes, that they might the more decently, and the more reſolutely keepe them.</p>
            <p>Our Generall Muſters, are inſtituted for a ſtrict ſurvay of Armes, and Munition: at which diſcovery, you ſhall ſee ſome Ruſtiques ſent into the field, clad in ruſt and duſt, rather then ſteele. Some of their Pikes and Muskets, as ſerviceable as Reeds and Pot-guns; as if they meant to play at boyes play, when their Country lies at ſtake. It is ill jeſting with edg'd tools; defect of armes is not laughing matter: it ſhould rather bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed, then ſlightly laughed at. Such jeſting may looſe a Kingdome in earneſt.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>David</hi> enter'd the Liſt no better ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then with a ſling, it is no warrant for us. He was a Prophet as will as a Souldier, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that victory, unto which that weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would prove ſufficient: or elſe <hi>David</hi> made choice of a ſling, becauſe his moſt experienced weapon.<note n="*" place="margin">Aurel. vict. <hi>Sucton.</hi>
               </note> As <hi>Domitian</hi> would uſe no armes but the bow, at which he was the wonder of dexterity. As the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2486:18"/>Benjamite could ſling, ſo hee could ſhoot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at a haires breadeth. <hi>David</hi> knew that it was as good not to take up armes, as not to know how to uſe them: Therefore he uſed his owne, refuſed the arm's of <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe unaccuſtomed, unpractiſed: That is the reaſon of his refuſall. <hi>And David ſaid unto Saul, I cannot goe with theſe, for I have not proved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Expoſitours are of opinion, that <hi>David</hi> refuſed <hi>Sauls</hi> armes becauſe unfit, unproportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: but I rather ſubſcribe to the fairer proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the golſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Lyra in Loc.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt intelligendum, &amp;c.</hi> It cannot with any probability be conceived, that <hi>Saul</hi> armed <hi>David</hi> with thoſe armes which were appropriated unto his owne body, their ſtatures being unequall, for <hi>Saul</hi> overtopped all Iſrael by the head, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.<note n="*" place="margin">Oſiander Martyr.</note> It is more probable that it is entitled <hi>Sauls</hi> armor, becauſe taken our of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.<note n="*" place="margin">Armis ſuis,] id eſt, Davidi datu à Saul, &amp; ipſius co pori accommodatis. Nam tanta fuit Saulis proceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ut arma ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Davidi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. int. Piſcator in locum.</note> Though <hi>David</hi> had beene heretofore <hi>Sauls</hi> armor bearer, yet the beſt expoſitors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that hitherto he had been no practitioner of arm's. Therfore <hi>David</hi> laies downe theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, not for his unfitneſſe to we are them, but to uſe them; being unskilful at them, unpractiſed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>I cannot go with theſe, for I have not proved them</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This reaſon of <hi>Davids</hi> refuſall doth intirnate, that hee is unfit to beare armes that knowes not how to uſe them:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſiander.</hi> Dr. Willet.</note> this knowledge comes not without proofe,<note place="margin">The neceſſity of a Military exerciſe.</note> without practiſe. Whence we may infer both the neceſſity, and the commodity of a Military exerciſe, of a Military diſcipline. Without this, whedn men ſhould bear armes for the ſervice of their Country, they will be forced
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2486:18"/>to fly to <hi>Davids</hi> refuſall here in my Text. <hi>I cannot goe with theſe: for I have not proved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finis Instrumenti conſiſtit in uſu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prooved from the end of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Inſtruments of warre (as all other) are made to no other end but to uſe them. And to uſe them without skill were to invert that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Hee fought with beaſts after the manner of men: but wee ſhould fight with men after the maner of<note n="*" place="margin">Et ſic bellum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belluis.</note> beaſts. The Denomination of an army is either <hi>Exercitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">From the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ination of an army.</note> an Army in Exerciſe; or <hi>Acies,</hi> an Army in battell aray. There is in the former, practice: In the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there is Order, and skill, the effect of that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Strength that is not directed by the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of Order, is like a horſe without a Rider, of it owne ſelfe it deſtroyes it ſelfe. As in every action it is odious to erre; ſo in the action of warre it is moſt dangerous. Becauſe one miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying is enough to overthrow an whole army. Wheron may depend the racke of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the loſſe of a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>In the infancy of warre before men knew any manner of military order:<note place="margin">From the effect of Military skill</note> the victory was ever carried by the ſtronger part. But ſince they have learned to order themſelves in ranke and file, the Conqueſt now is not ſo proper to the ſtrength of men, as to this experimented Order. <hi>Nemo facere metuit qui ſe bene didiciſſe confidit.</hi> The experience of skill makes a man both dexterous and couragious. A multitude that is diſordered is diſheartened, and no way able to withſtand an inferiour number that ſhall aſſault them with order, and skill. If our gate be warlike, it is Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that muſt ſet us on our feet. That body of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2486:19"/>an Army is but <hi>inutile truncus,</hi> an unprofitable bulke, where the feet of exerciſe are fetter'd, and the limmes of Practiſe benumm'd. <hi>Quantitatis nulla est efficacia.</hi> Quantity is of no force. It is qualitie that muſt denominate our forces. The moſt numerous Armies have not alwayes carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away the victory. Witneſſe the victory of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> over <hi>Darius,</hi> Of <hi>Ceſar</hi> over <hi>Pompey,</hi> Of <hi>Hannibul</hi> over the Romane Conſuls, Of <hi>Edward</hi> the blacke Prince over <hi>Iohn</hi> king of France in that moſt renowned battell of Poicters. Where not the moſt, but the beſt (though feweſt) ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were Lords of the Field.</p>
            <p>Then what followes but a diligent Practiſe of that Martiall Aphoriſme?<note place="margin">Vegetius.</note> 
               <hi>Formentur Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes omni armorum exercitio, uſuque Militiae.</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers muſt bee trained up in all kinde of Martiall exerciſe. In the right uſe of their Armes, in all the beates of the Drumme, in all Military moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to march wel, to face, to wheele, to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march, to double rankes, and files; And to doe all theſe either by the ſigne, or word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Without this knowledge ſouldiers are more expoſed to the ſlaughter than to the fight.</p>
            <p>The Jewes though miraculouſly victorious,<note place="margin">From Example</note> and ſecurely confident of the protection of a Deity yet they were diſciplined in armes. The traine Bands of <hi>Abrabam, Moſes, Ioſuah, Saul, David, Salomon, Iehoſaphat, Aſa, Vzziab</hi> make it very probable, that the Jewes had a Schoole for the warriour, as well as for the Prophet. The antient <hi>Gaules</hi> (that moſt warlike Nation) were ſo accuſtomed to the bearing of Armes, that they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2486:19"/>made their Coucell houſe an armory, they went armed unto their Councels. Where the <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite</hi> of an Oration was not the clapping of hands, but the clattering of Armes. It was Military exerciſe, and experience that enlarged both Greece and Rome into Monarchies.</p>
            <p>We alſo have a Cuſtomary Annuall training of our Counties: But ſometimes ſo triviall,<note place="margin">A Check to moderne T ning.</note> ſo ſuperficiall, that it improves rather our ſport, than our skill. The ignorant Ruſtiques winke when they give fire. The Captaine winkes at it, and the ſpectators laugh at it. Such a milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſcipline is ſitter for a May-game than for a field. It may be heartily wiſhed that their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Inſtructors were more induſtrious, their training more frequent, and ſerious. Let a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent exerciſe improve our skill: Leſt when we are unexpectedly provoked unto Armes, there ſhould bee <hi>impar Congreſſus,</hi> The experienced enemy ſhould over match us, And the want of Practiſe in the exerciſe of Armes ſhould drive us to the Confeſſion of our ignorance in the words of my Text, wee <hi>cannot goe with theſe: for</hi> we <hi>have not proved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I leave a generall importunity,<note place="margin">Application to the Company.</note> and come unto the particular Opportunity, the preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: The Martiall body of my diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt ſpent.<note n="*" place="margin">Adagium.</note> 
               <hi>Res ad Triarios redijt.</hi> The Rere of my diſcourſe ſhall bring in the Rere, the antient Quarter Band of the <hi>Triarij,</hi> Thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that were moſt compleatly diſciplined: Who were the very Soule from whence the body of the Army had both life and motion.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2486:20"/>
            <p>To you I doe now direct my exhortation, who are the Nurſing Fathers, and the Generous Aſſociates of our Nurſery of Armes. I have proved unto you the lawfulneſſe of the Generall Action of warre, The neceſſitie and choice of the Inſtruments of warre. But what is munition without men? Or what are men without skill? And where is skill ſooner attained than in the Schoole of Martiall Exerciſe? It would be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous tarrying from this Schoole untill our Enemies whip us to it. A rod of Iron is ſoone made for the back of the Lazy Trivant. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as readineſſe and dexteritie in Martial diſcipline would ſtartle the Enemy, for feare he ſhould be ſcourged with his owne rod.</p>
            <p>Then let not your Nurſery of Armes miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like an untimely birth: Or ſo faire a Garden (like <hi>Ionahs</hi> Gourd) periſh in a night. Preferre not a Bowling greene before a Military Garden: but rather follow a Captaine, than a Jacke. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation is convenient, but Practiſe is neceſſary:<note n="*" place="margin">Jure ab Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotele Phale as reprehenditur, quod in deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſua civitate nullam Mart is imaginem deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaverit. <hi>Ariſt. polit. lib. 2. c. 5.</hi>
               </note> And that in the time of Peace.<note n="*" place="margin">Such ever taſte the leſſe troubles in the tempeſt of war, which ſaile with a martiall foreſight in the time of Peace.</note> In Peace to provide for war is the beſt ſecurity. The wings of our Peace are not ſo clipped, but ſhe may take the wings of a Dove, and fly away with our Olive Branch. Iſrael had peace forty yeeres, yet even then their aged Peace did take her flight, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.11.12. Wee cannot be ſecurely confident of peace, and reſt, until we have letters of Eaſe from the King of heaven. But we finde no ſuch Patent upon Record. Though your Land bee intail'd unto you and your Heires: Though you enjoy it by the firmeſt Title; yet a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2486:20"/>time may come when it cannot bee held by any other Title but the ſword. And then they that ſhew the beſt Inſtruments, and the beſt skill, will have the poſſeſſion.<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 24.6.</note> 
               <hi>By wiſe Counſell thou ſhalt make thy warre,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> They which are to be Counſellors in a warlique Action ſhould be men of Practiſe.</p>
            <p>This honourable City may be compared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſea-faring Tribe of Zebulon, that was a Haven for ſhips. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.9. And ſo is this. The men of that Tribe were expert in warre: They could keepe ranke, they were skilfull at all the Inſtruments of warre. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. And ſo may the men of this City; If there would more of them, and more often frequent the Schoole of warre. One vertue of a ſouldier is ſilence, A Maiden vertue: Maides muſt be ſeene, not heard. Souldiers though they muſt not bee heard, yet they muſt be ſeene. It will redound more to their honour than ſhame to make a frequent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. The ſpoiles of Salmacis were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſweat or blood. Your Military Exerciſe coſts you no blood. You may well ſpare a little excrement, a little ſweat.<note n="*" place="margin">See, we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid here in Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dah, how much more if we come to Keilah againſt the hoſt of the Philiſtins. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.</note> It will coſt you blood abroad. Then let not the melting of a little ſweat melt the courage of your induſtrious reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the attaining of ſo honorable a ſcience.</p>
            <p>Truly Honourable, Martiall Deſert being the antient Principall Herald for the Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Moſt of them from Majeſty to Gentry, from the Emperor to the Squire have quarter'd their Coates of Honour from this Quarter. The Sword of the Warriour findes an honourable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2486:21"/>Parallel with the ſword of the Magiſtrate. They are both drawn for the execution of Juſtice. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and skill are requiſite to the managing of them both. Let the Magiſtrate countenance the ſouldier in the time of Peace. And the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſhall defend the Magiſtrate in the time of warre.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Our Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries record that it was an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto our Chevalry when they were abroad. That the Church of England was upon her knees for them.</note>In the meane time that bleſſed Church (whereof you are members) will not be out of Practiſe: but make uſe of her ſpirituall weapons. Though ſhe dare not lift up the ſword in battell with <hi>Ioſuah:</hi> Shee will not ceaſe to lift up her hands in prayer with <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Oratiocoelos penetrat, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes in terra vincit. <hi>Origen.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Preces &amp; Iejunium ſunt Arma Eccleſiae.</hi> Prayer and Faſting are the weapons of the Church. Her frequent, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Devotion ſhall be this: That the Lord of Hoſts would repaire the breaches of his<note n="*" place="margin">My beloved is a Garden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12.</note> inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Military Garden, his Church Militant here on earth. That hee would preſerve thoſe three principall borders which amongſt us hee hath planted, and united under one Government. That as that God of peace hath taught us thoſe things which belong unto our peace: ſo that Man of warre would teach our hands to warre, and our fingers to fight; that neither the ſword of the Magiſtrate, nor of the warriour may bee drawne wrongfully, or in vaine. That the end of our temporall warfare may be a bleſſed peace upon earth: and of our ſpirituall, an eternall peace in the heavens. Unto which Peace the God of Peace bring us all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2486:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
